<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rash duellist disected: with the inconveniencies that attend him.  By way of essay</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B43762</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">688635907</idno>
  <idno type="VID">212056</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240859300</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 688635907</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 688635907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R284</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B43762)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 212056)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2998:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rash duellist disected: with the inconveniencies that attend him.  By way of essay</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Phillip Brooksby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Dueling --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fighting (Psychology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:212056:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:212056:2"/>
            <p>THE RASH DUELLIST DISECTED: WITH THE INCONVENIENCIES That Attend HIM.</p>
            <p>By Way of ESSAY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Phillip Brooksby.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:212056:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:212056:3"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>SOund judgement</hi> has not <hi>capacitated</hi> me for the <hi>State,</hi> nor has <hi>sober Learning</hi> qualified me for the <hi>Church:</hi> no, I am not <hi>acute</hi> enough for the <hi>Knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Law,</hi> nor <hi>profound</hi> enough for <hi>the Mysterious Gospel.</hi> Therefore having (perhaps) unadvisedly run my self into a <hi>little Tract,</hi> that borders upon <hi>Policy</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> I have endeavour'd to steer my course so, as that I may not <hi>fall foul</hi> on that <hi>Rock,</hi> nor be <hi>swallowed up</hi> in this <hi>Gulph:</hi> For I intend nothing conteined in this <hi>Essay,</hi> as <hi>counsel</hi> from the <hi>Bar,</hi> or <hi>reproof</hi> from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> but only as the <hi>Remarques</hi> of a <hi>Moralist.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:212056:4"/>
            <p> If thou expectest an <hi>accompt</hi> of the <hi>motives</hi> that induc'd me to this <hi>Rashness:</hi> know, that being by <hi>Birth</hi> an <hi>Englishman,</hi> and by <hi>Education</hi> an <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demian,</hi> by the <hi>Affection</hi> I have for my <hi>Country,</hi> and out of the <hi>respect</hi> I owe to my <hi>Mother,</hi> the <hi>University,</hi> I thought my self <hi>obliged</hi> (at least to <hi>endeavour</hi>) not to be a <hi>disparagement</hi> to either: And since it lyes not in my way, to contribute to the <hi>making</hi> of <hi>Combes,</hi> nor <hi>bringing in</hi> of <hi>Honey:</hi> that <hi>I</hi> might <hi>exempt</hi> my self from the <hi>Imputation</hi> of <hi>Drone, I</hi> resolv'd to busie my self, though about <hi>nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this will not satisfie thee, but that having <hi>read</hi> such a <hi>Trifle,</hi> thou must fall into <hi>great admiration,</hi> and <hi>many questions,</hi> such as, <hi>Why would this fellow pretend to Write,</hi> &amp;c. Let all thy <hi>Wonder</hi> cease, and all thy <hi>questions</hi> be resolved in this, That <hi>Few Men, who have not Wit enough to Write well, have judgement enough to discern that they Write ill.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:212056:4"/>
            <head>An Essay of Duelling.</head>
            <p>WHile we conceive <hi>Duelling</hi> as an <hi>Action:</hi> under that <hi>Conception,</hi> we must have recourse to <hi>Circumstances</hi> for its <hi>Discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating Epethets</hi> of <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad:</hi> But these are so various both in <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Kind,</hi> that it will be very difficult to reduce the <hi>Thesis</hi> to any <hi>certainty,</hi> without mustering up a <hi>Volume</hi> of Instances out of <hi>God's Revenge against Murder,</hi> or some Book like it; and so by the several <hi>descants</hi> upon every <hi>Individual Duel,</hi> to deduce Arguments to prove one general <hi>Assertion: (Viz.) That all Duels are unlawful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But since I intend a Discourse more <hi>Concise,</hi> and (I hope) more to the <hi>Purpose,</hi> than that comes to, I designedly omit the <hi>Enumeration</hi> of that <hi>long train</hi> of <hi>Circumstances</hi> which wait on our <hi>Actions:</hi> instancing only in the most general motive that enduceth men to <hi>Duelling;</hi> which I look upon as the proper <hi>Basis</hi> on which the stress of my present Discourse ought to rely. This Motive I have generally observed to be the <hi>preservation</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> and look upon it as the <hi>end</hi> (or more properly the <hi>beginning</hi>) of all <hi>Duels;</hi> and is indeed <hi>a very fair mark to aim at:</hi> so that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:212056:5"/>nothing can redound to the disparagement of the <hi>Archer,</hi> but his proving so <hi>Purblind,</hi> as not rightly to distinguish between the <hi>reality</hi> and the <hi>resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance;</hi> or so <hi>Ʋnskilful,</hi> as never to come neer the <hi>White.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I am fearful that I shall too easily make it apper that many <hi>Gentlemen</hi> are very <hi>short-sighted</hi> in this <hi>Particular,</hi> and that either through the <hi>false Vizards</hi> they have put upon <hi>Honour,</hi> or the <hi>unjust estimates</hi> they make of it, they often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Fight</hi> for the <hi>shadow</hi> instead of the <hi>substance,</hi> and (through that <hi>mistake) destroy</hi> what they so Zealously endeavour to <hi>maintain.</hi> A <hi>true Diamond</hi> is indeed a Jewel of Price, but it is Rivalled by <hi>Glass</hi> and <hi>Pebbles; Iron</hi> may wear a <hi>superficies</hi> as curiously <hi>Engraved</hi> as the <hi>purest Steel,</hi> but it is not so familiar and kind to the <hi>Loadstone: Brass</hi> may bear the same <hi>impress</hi> with <hi>Gold,</hi> but it cannot put a <hi>cheat</hi> upon the <hi>Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone:</hi> and as for <hi>Honour,</hi> I Fancy it is as distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishable by its <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>genuine marks,</hi> as any of these.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Touchstone</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> I take to be <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> nothing certainly can be so true a <hi>Gage,</hi> or so just a <hi>Standard</hi> of it, as the <hi>Ethicks:</hi> So
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:212056:5"/>that I shall adventure to make this general assertion: (in spight of <hi>Hectors) Viz. That it is impossible for a Man to be truly Honourable, who is not truly Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi> And though Men have either carelesly, or industriously suffered that one great <hi>embelishment, Magnanimity;</hi> as it were to <hi>Monopolize</hi> all <hi>Vertue,</hi> making a convertible Proposition of it. <hi>That no man can be Honourable, but he that is Stout:</hi> and again, <hi>That no Man can be Stout, but he must be Honourable:</hi> Yet I believe the rest of the <hi>Moral Vertues</hi> would take it very <hi>unkindly,</hi> so to be shouldred out of doors, but that they see <hi>Magnanimity</hi> so grosely abused, as it is even by those who pretend to be the greatest admirers of it. How this <hi>Errour</hi> came to escape <hi>Conviction,</hi> I know not, but certainly 'tis the greatest imaginable; and carries <hi>Pawn</hi> (I am confident) with none but such as <hi>really are,</hi> or however would be <hi>thought Ranck Hectors:</hi> And even <hi>such</hi> quickly find themselves hugely disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in their ill-grounded hopes: For whatever they purpose to themselves in the midst of their <hi>huf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing,</hi> yet while they are endevouring to impose the name of <hi>Bubble</hi> upon others, they become the greatest ones themselves, owing their <hi>Greatness</hi> to a <hi>vapour,</hi> till they <hi>break</hi> into <hi>Nothing.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:212056:6"/>And after they have convinced the whole World by their <hi>Duels</hi> and <hi>Murders,</hi> what undaunted Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits they have, for which they expect <hi>Adoration</hi> from all that pass by <hi>them,</hi> they are forced to content <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves</hi> with the <hi>applauses</hi> of two or three of their <hi>Brethren,</hi> and the <hi>submissive respect</hi> of some few of their Creatures: And I make my appeal to any <hi>sober</hi> and <hi>rational</hi> Man, whether a person notorious for <hi>Lying,</hi> a Prodigious <hi>Sot,</hi> an abominable <hi>Lecher,</hi> or the like, gain the least <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Esteem</hi> with any, but such as are like himself, though he be the <hi>stoutest man living.</hi> For my part, I would no more <hi>espouse</hi> such an acquaintance, because of his <hi>Courage,</hi> than I would chuse to <hi>Marry a beastly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Strumpet,</hi> because she had a <hi>sprightly eye,</hi> or some other commendable <hi>feature:</hi> and do not find any <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachresis</hi> in the <hi>Analogy,</hi> more, than that the latter is a companion the least mischevious and dangerous of the two.</p>
            <p>Thus it is my opinion, that a man who is every way <hi>morally vicious,</hi> excepting in his Courage, ought to live with less <hi>Honour,</hi> than he that is in all other respects <hi>morrally good,</hi> and well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished, though a <hi>Coward,</hi> for <hi>Courage</hi> is the <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and if a man wants it, 'tis not his <hi>fault</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:212056:6"/>but his <hi>misfortune: Nature</hi> is <hi>unkind,</hi> and he is <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy;</hi> he is <hi>good</hi> to the uttermost of his <hi>Power,</hi> by <hi>suppressing Nature</hi> when 'tis <hi>rebellious,</hi> but he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>encourage</hi> it when 'tis <hi>faint-hearted:</hi> he finds it <hi>deficient</hi> in his <hi>heart,</hi> and therefore supplies that <hi>chasm</hi> by a more than <hi>common liberality</hi> of his <hi>hands, affabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of his <hi>Tougue,</hi> &amp;c. And since he wants one <hi>branch</hi> in the <hi>Tree of Honour,</hi> he so orders and disposes of the rest, that they <hi>flourish</hi> to the <hi>making up of that Breach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus while the Gentleman I mentioned even now, makes <hi>necessity</hi> of a <hi>Vertue,</hi> by <hi>pressing his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to vindicate the Quarrels of his many other vices,</hi> this makes a <hi>vertue</hi> of <hi>necessity,</hi> by <hi>marshalling all his other excellencies to the concealinent of this deformity.</hi> While <hi>he</hi> has <hi>a mind so beclouded, as to abate much of the lusture of his Fortitude; This</hi> has a <hi>Soul</hi> so <hi>serene,</hi> as even <hi>to lend Rays to his Pusillanimity.</hi> While <hi>he Arrests</hi> his <hi>Magnanimity to pay the debts of</hi> his <hi>drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enness,</hi> this by his <hi>temperance, plays the good Husband,</hi> and <hi>contracts none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that I intend this for a <hi>Panegyrique</hi> of <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardice,</hi> but only by this <hi>Antithesis</hi> to evince how grosely they mistake, who think <hi>all Honour placed in a readiness to go into the Field upon every the least occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion;</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:212056:7"/>and him to be the <hi>only Gentleman,</hi> that will do this, though in all other matters he be <hi>vitiated,</hi> even to a <hi>Debauch.</hi> But taking what I have said for granted, the consequence will be this: That <hi>Courage</hi> alone cannot <hi>maintain,</hi> much less purchase <hi>Honour,</hi> unless there be a <hi>consent,</hi> and a <hi>combination</hi> of the <hi>other vertues</hi> to assist it. Arms look very <hi>naked</hi> without <hi>Suporters:</hi> And let the <hi>Soloecism</hi> appear how great soever, 'tis a <hi>Truth</hi> that <hi>Affability</hi> and <hi>Meekness</hi> is the best <hi>varnish</hi> to <hi>Courage,</hi> which (like <hi>vineger</hi>) will fret and feed upon it self, unless it be allayed with <hi>Water,</hi> or some more innocent <hi>Liquor.</hi> But the mischief of it is, that Men are now generally become their own <hi>Heralds,</hi> they will not remember that <hi>Honor est in honorante;</hi> nor be beholding to the World for that <hi>Worship,</hi> which they conceive to be a just <hi>Debt</hi> to their <hi>Merit.</hi> They grow furious, and are like <hi>Nebuchadnezer:</hi> for putting all men (like <hi>Neba</hi>) to Death that will not <hi>Idolize</hi> these <hi>Images</hi> of their own setting up. But if these would consider that their <hi>Reputation</hi> lyes in other Mens hands, they would certainly remember that it is rather to be <hi>won</hi> with <hi>gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and <hi>civility,</hi> than by <hi>rigor</hi> and <hi>force.</hi> The suddain snatching of so <hi>brittle</hi> a <hi>Mettle</hi> may <hi>crack</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:212056:7"/>it, when Care and soft usage may preserve it <hi>entire.</hi> And the best advice that can be given in this case, is certainly this: <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Men would be so <hi>Ingenious</hi> as to get a <hi>Reputation</hi> before they grow so very <hi>Zealous</hi> to keep it.</p>
            <p>But there is a Second sort of <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> who would take this advice as an <hi>Affront,</hi> because they come not under the <hi>scandal</hi> of <hi>Debauchery:</hi> And yet many of these are <hi>Peccant</hi> in a more than commendable <hi>forwardness</hi> to receive <hi>affronts,</hi> though not so ready to give them. These (in their own conceits) have <hi>Honours</hi> of a most Prodigious <hi>Magnitude,</hi> and indeed <hi>swel'd</hi> to that <hi>Disproportion,</hi> that it is rather to be feared they are <hi>puft up</hi> with a <hi>Tympany of Pride,</hi> than <hi>consolidated</hi> with firm <hi>Nobility.</hi> If a Man that has not the <hi>Breeding</hi> of the <hi>Town</hi> come into their Company, 'tis impossible he should <hi>live:</hi> Alas! this <hi>dull Animal</hi> cannot breath in their <hi>Aura.</hi> There is <hi>Civility</hi> in its <hi>Purity,</hi> when a Man that does not understand himself can neither look, speak, nor do any thing but what is taken for an abuse: If there arise any <hi>Dispute,</hi> he must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer nothing in opposition, but what must be Usher'd in with a <hi>by your pardon Sir, I think 'tis so</hi>—And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:212056:8"/>indeed the <hi>ill-bred Gentleman</hi> may gain a <hi>Fortune</hi> in the Country with half the <hi>ceremony</hi> that he must here make use of to <hi>Arm</hi> himself against a <hi>Challenge.</hi> I confess these <hi>clowns</hi> are unhappy in their want of <hi>Education,</hi> and either by their ill <hi>Managery</hi> of their <hi>actions,</hi> or their <hi>foolish retorts</hi> in a dispute, they oftentimes become <hi>rediculous</hi> in <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,</hi> and <hi>abusive</hi> to <hi>others.</hi> But yet methinks an <hi>ingenious Soul</hi> should make these <hi>Occurrences</hi> the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of his <hi>Laughter,</hi> rather than of his <hi>Anger.</hi> I would have <hi>Honour</hi> like the <hi>Palm-Tree,</hi> to <hi>rise and appear vigorous under any weight,</hi> and not like the <hi>Plant</hi> we call <hi>Sensitive,</hi> to <hi>shrink in at every little Touch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the two <hi>instances</hi> already mentioned come not fully to my Purpose: the <hi>disparity</hi> is such that it seldom proceeds to a <hi>Duel:</hi> For the <hi>Hector</hi> or <hi>Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin,</hi> is one with whom scarce any man will <hi>Fight,</hi> and the <hi>Pedant</hi> or <hi>Buffoon,</hi> is one who will scarce <hi>Fight</hi> with any Man. The former is usually Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with, and the latter commonly lets fall the <hi>Suit</hi> before it comes to a <hi>Tryal:</hi> Therefore before you bring the <hi>Man of Honour</hi> upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> you must bring him a <hi>Competitour,</hi> one that is a Gentleman, and in all respects lays as great a claim to Gallantry as himself; when such meet upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:212056:8"/>the least shadow of an <hi>affront</hi> arises a <hi>Quarrel,</hi> which is presently <hi>seconded</hi> with a <hi>Challenge,</hi> and ends in a <hi>Duel,</hi> as if it were impossible for these <hi>Cocks</hi> of the <hi>Game</hi> to see one another without <hi>Animosity.</hi> If they cannot be happy in a better <hi>occasion,</hi> the taking of the <hi>Wall</hi> shall serve the turn, and if either attempts to go next it, his Adversary shall do his best to <hi>verifie</hi> the <hi>Proverb,</hi> by endeavouring him to prove him the <hi>weakest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But almost daily experience informs us of worse effects of the <hi>Sword,</hi> than those we hear of in <hi>rencounters,</hi> of which, if we inquire into the <hi>causes</hi> and <hi>originals,</hi> we shall find them comprized chiefly in three <hi>Heads:</hi> namely, PLAY, WINE and WOMEN. And whosoever will be at the trouble of keeping a <hi>Diurnal</hi> of the <hi>Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions</hi> of <hi>this City,</hi> I dare say, shall scarce need any other <hi>Common-place,</hi> to refer all the <hi>Duels</hi> that have been fought for some years past, and will be Fought for some years to come, than <hi>These.</hi> How frequent (I may say constant) effects of this Nature do we daily find to be the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural consequences</hi> of <hi>Play? Passion</hi> is its <hi>unseparable Companion,</hi> and if <hi>Fortune</hi> prove ever so little <hi>adverse,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:212056:9"/>the <hi>Loser</hi> takes occasion to <hi>Quarrel,</hi> not only at <hi>Her,</hi> but the very <hi>person she assists,</hi> though (perhaps) a <hi>Bosom Friend,</hi> or a <hi>neer Relation.</hi> As if he resolved to <hi>humour</hi> his <hi>Fortune</hi> with his <hi>Carriage,</hi> and scorned to <hi>behave</hi> himself <hi>well,</hi> when the <hi>Dice</hi> run <hi>ill:</hi> Every unlucky <hi>throw</hi> puts him into an <hi>Outrage,</hi> and being grown <hi>desperate</hi> upon the loss of his <hi>money,</hi> he <hi>Pawns</hi> his <hi>Reason:</hi> Then follow the <hi>God-dam-you's,</hi> and <hi>Plague-confound-you's:</hi> Nay, and 'tis much if he give not the <hi>Lye,</hi> or the <hi>Son of a Whore,</hi> nor is it at all to be <hi>admired,</hi> if having broken out into <hi>Prophaness,</hi> he keeps not within the <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Civility.</hi> These (I confess) are <hi>indignities</hi> not to be endured, and let a Man he never so well <hi>Armed</hi> with <hi>Moderation</hi> or <hi>Friendship,</hi> yet such <hi>assaults</hi> as these, presently make a <hi>breach,</hi> and force him to <hi>Proclaim open War.</hi> So that in effect <hi>Speering</hi>'s <hi>Ordinary</hi> proves the ready way to <hi>Lambs-Conduit;</hi> and a <hi>smooth Table</hi> becomes as <hi>fatal</hi> to throw <hi>Dice</hi> upon, as a <hi>Drum-head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is <hi>Wine</hi> a less <hi>incendiary</hi> to these kind of <hi>Heats</hi> and <hi>Quarrels,</hi> than <hi>Play:</hi> Nay, most commonly it is the <hi>first mover,</hi> not only of the <hi>remoter Effects,</hi> but also of the more <hi>immediate causes;</hi> for <hi>Gameing</hi> and <hi>Whoring</hi> would be <hi>meagre</hi> and <hi>disregarded vices,</hi> were they not <hi>pampered up</hi> with <hi>Drinking.</hi> This takes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:212056:9"/>away those <hi>Rubs</hi> and <hi>Obstacles</hi> which <hi>Sobrie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Dictates to our <hi>Reason;</hi> and removes those <hi>Boomes,</hi> which a <hi>temperate resolution</hi> had set up as <hi>Guides,</hi> and <hi>non ultra's,</hi> and while we miss these, no wonder if we <hi>run our selves a ground:</hi> Every Man when he is <hi>Sober,</hi> knows that to play with <hi>Rooks</hi> and <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates,</hi> is to make <hi>Ducks</hi> and <hi>Drakes</hi> of his <hi>Money;</hi> and yet one <hi>drunken sit</hi> removes all his <hi>Jealousies,</hi> and then he will <hi>venture himself</hi> with any <hi>Fellows,</hi> and <hi>his money</hi> at <hi>any rate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But supposing him so <hi>prudently drunk,</hi> as not to be <hi>drawn</hi> into <hi>Play,</hi> 'tis odds; but you find him so <hi>foolishly Quarrelsom,</hi> as that way to run himself into <hi>equal inconveniencies.</hi> Not one in twenty but is so <hi>grosely abusive,</hi> that it is beyond the patience of a <hi>stranger</hi> to endure it: Nay, even his most <hi>intimate acquaintance</hi> know not where to have him; their good <hi>advice</hi> is <hi>misconstrued,</hi> and their <hi>actions</hi> of <hi>friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship mislikt;</hi> and unless they have less <hi>wine,</hi> or more <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it</hi> in their <hi>Heads</hi> than he, you may rationally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect one or more of the Company in the literal fence <hi>Bloody-drunk.</hi> But it may so happen that they are <hi>intercepted,</hi> and these <hi>Intestine</hi> (I cannot call them <hi>civil</hi>) <hi>Broyls</hi> reconcil'd: Yet the <hi>mischief</hi> does not commonly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd there, they do but like <hi>neighbouring
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:212056:10"/>Princes,</hi> who in the heat of <hi>War</hi> make a <hi>League,</hi> and both joyn against a <hi>common Enemy.</hi> They cannot walk (or rather reel) the Street without offering an <hi>affront</hi> to every one they meet. The best qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified <hi>Gentleman,</hi> or the <hi>modestest Lady</hi> cannot pass them without a <hi>Rudeness</hi> offered: So that tracing them from the <hi>Tavern</hi> to <hi>Whetstones-Park,</hi> you will assuredly find some <hi>drops</hi> of <hi>Blood,</hi> or hear of some <hi>work</hi> cut out for the next <hi>Morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then indeed begins a <hi>Tragi-comoedy,</hi> enough to make <hi>Democritus</hi> look <hi>serious,</hi> or <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitus laugh:</hi> Were there a thousand <hi>Craessus's,</hi> 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible they should contain themselves, seeing these <hi>Asses mumbling Thistles:</hi> One of these awakes in <hi>discontent,</hi> just remembring that he did <hi>challenge</hi> a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and appointed him a place of <hi>meeting,</hi> but has forgotten where: A Second remembers the place, but knows nothing else of the <hi>Quarrel.</hi> A third remembers the <hi>Gentleman</hi> to have been most grosely abused, without any cause at all. Well, after this <hi>coucil of war</hi> has debated the thing, and consulted <hi>their Honours,</hi> the result of all is a necessity of <hi>Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Thus as the <hi>Pope</hi> proves himself <hi>infallible</hi> by maintaining the <hi>Errours</hi> he runs into: so these <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen justifie</hi> all their <hi>actions</hi> to be <hi>Honourable</hi> by <hi>vindicating</hi> those that are <hi>otherwise.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:212056:10"/>
            <p> And now I am to beg pardon of the <hi>Ladys</hi> for <hi>shouldring</hi> them into any concern in this <hi>Tragedy:</hi> How they came to be engaged, I know not, but according to my observation, they are rather the <hi>occasions</hi> of it, than <hi>actors</hi> in it. We have a <hi>saying,</hi> that <hi>there is seldom any mischief done, but a woman is at one end of it.</hi> But in this case, the <hi>mischief</hi> proceeds most commanly from our <hi>foolish zeal,</hi> not from their <hi>instigations.</hi> I conceive the <hi>Precedence</hi> due to those that are <hi>honourable,</hi> and therefore I shall first <hi>instance</hi> in them; such (I mean) as have preserved their <hi>reputations,</hi> and are esteemed <hi>Vertuous:</hi> and certainly no such person can be thought <hi>accessary</hi> to our <hi>follies,</hi> or a <hi>fomentour</hi> of our <hi>vices,</hi> but it (as the <hi>Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> calls it) <hi>causa per accidens,</hi> as in this case.</p>
            <p>Supposing a <hi>Lady Young, Rich,</hi> and <hi>Handsom,</hi> having done that, you suppose her surrounded with <hi>Servants,</hi> of whom possibly she <hi>Affects one more Peculiarly,</hi> and he that is thus <hi>happy</hi> or <hi>unfortunate,</hi> (call it which you please) must either <hi>Relinquish</hi> his <hi>hopes,</hi> or <hi>Maintain</hi> them with his <hi>Sword.</hi> If he be <hi>Victorious</hi> in the first <hi>Encounter,</hi> he shall meet with a Second, and if there be Twenty of these <hi>Rivals,</hi> they shall have the <hi>Fate</hi> of <hi>Red breasts, shut</hi> up in an <hi>Aviary:</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:212056:11"/>all must dye save one, and none must enjoy this <hi>Venus,</hi> but the <hi>God of War:</hi> While each has set up a resolution not to desire her <hi>Affection,</hi> but <hi>win</hi> it; which to effect, they propose no other way, than by <hi>destroying</hi> the <hi>object</hi> of it: and yet this goes for a piece of <hi>Gallantry,</hi> not only <hi>Justifiable,</hi> but <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious:</hi> such an example of <hi>Knight-Errantry,</hi> as that a Man cannot prove himself a <hi>Gentleman</hi> without it. I confess I admire Actions of this Nature, as much as any Man, but it is for the <hi>rashness</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> of them: for I cannot fancy they have any <hi>rational aim</hi> or <hi>design.</hi> Do men hereby propose to themselves enjoyment of the <hi>Lady?</hi> To me it seems very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable that such a <hi>wontan</hi> as we have already sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, should love a Man for no other reason but that he has <hi>Murthered</hi> him she formerly inclined to: or to reward the <hi>improvident Husband</hi> with the <hi>Grapes,</hi> because she chatcht him cutting down the <hi>supporters</hi> of the <hi>Vine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But allowing this to be well received on the <hi>Ladies</hi> part, there remains yet another difficulty to be removed before it can proceed to a <hi>Sack-posset:</hi> there is a <hi>place <hi>hight</hi> Newgate,</hi> and a <hi>Creature <hi>ycleped,</hi>
               </hi> a <hi>Judge,</hi> that will have something to say to Mr. <hi>Bridegroom, in Potentia,</hi> who perhaps forbids
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:212056:11"/>the <hi>Banns,</hi> and so deprives him of the opportunity of being called <hi>handsom Man,</hi> as he is going to <hi>Church,</hi> but gives him as fair a one as he is going to the <hi>Gallows.</hi> Thus falls this <hi>Champion</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> a <hi>Martyr</hi> to <hi>Love,</hi> and he that fancied himself to live with all <hi>Imaginable esteem,</hi> and <hi>repute,</hi> now dyes with <hi>unconceiveable reproach</hi> and <hi>disgrace,</hi> confessing that
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honour</hi> in <hi>Youth</hi> is but an itch o'th' blood,</l>
                  <l>Of doing things extravagantly good.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, I confess, of all instances this last, as 'tis the most excusable in it <hi>self,</hi> so 'tis the least <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable</hi> in the <hi>consequences</hi> of it: because he that suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers is a <hi>single person,</hi> and <hi>pays</hi> no <hi>debts</hi> but those of his own <hi>contracting:</hi> whereas in some cases, though the <hi>Halter</hi> puts an end to a Mans <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> together, yet the <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Misery</hi> survives to his Posterity (if he has any.) 'Tis possible the <hi>Pendant Gentleman</hi> may leave a Widow and Orphans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing his Dishonour, and their own Misfortune: for while he makes a <hi>forfiture</hi> of his <hi>estate</hi> to the King, and his <hi>good Name</hi> to the <hi>VVorld,</hi> he Entails upon them nothing but <hi>Seandal</hi> and <hi>Beggery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As these Disasters therefore are not always oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned by <hi>Civil</hi> WOMEN, so neither are they always the <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>Love:</hi> For if a Gentleman be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:212056:12"/>handing a Lady along the Street (whatever she be) how <hi>unmercifully stout</hi> does he grow upon a suddain, a Man cannot pass by this <hi>shrine,</hi> but he must do it <hi>reverence,</hi> at least by keeping a <hi>fit distance,</hi> if casually he gives her the least <hi>justle,</hi> 'tis ten to one but this <hi>zealous Gallant,</hi> out of an <hi>ambition</hi> to <hi>ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate</hi> himself, and appear a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>mettle,</hi> comes out with his <hi>Damme! what d'ee mean.</hi> or <hi>how now Logger-head, what's that for?</hi> and either he draws himself, or gives the other provocation enough to do it. Is not this the <hi>Mode</hi> of the <hi>Town:</hi> and do not seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral occurrences like these happen in a Year? Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that many times men lose their lives in vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the <hi>reputation</hi> of a <hi>common Whore;</hi> as if <hi>Honour</hi> (by a kind of <hi>Antiperistasis</hi>) were to be maintained by things <hi>dishonourable,</hi> or (like the <hi>Fig-tree) did flourish best,</hi> when planted near to <hi>Rue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having <hi>traced</hi> these <hi>disturbed</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasant streams</hi> through all their <hi>by-paths,</hi> and <hi>Moeanders,</hi> from their several <hi>spring-heads,</hi> down to the <hi>Red-Sea,</hi> whether they all tend. I think it time to cast an eye toward the <hi>Mountain tops:</hi> Those (I mean) of the <hi>Nobility</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentry,</hi> who either by their <hi>Valour</hi> or <hi>Wisdom,</hi> are grown to a <hi>greatness</hi> and <hi>height</hi> above the <hi>level</hi> of other men. To whom I intend
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:212056:12"/>not to be so unjust, as to endeavour to <hi>raze</hi> or <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> those <hi>Pyramids,</hi> which either their <hi>Ancestours</hi> or <hi>themselves</hi> have erected as perpetual <hi>Memorials</hi> of their <hi>Honour.</hi> And indeed, could I be so <hi>malicious,</hi> or <hi>daring,</hi> to attempt this, how strangely would my endeavours be intercepted, when our <hi>English Noble-men,</hi> like those of <hi>Troy,</hi> put forth their <hi>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting hand,</hi> to their <hi>own destruction,</hi> and themselves become instrumental to the <hi>Demollishing</hi> of their own <hi>Babel?</hi> If two of these <hi>Structures</hi> stand neer together, lifting up their <hi>heads</hi> of equal height, what <hi>aemulation</hi> and <hi>envy</hi> does it beget, <hi>one</hi> must be <hi>pulled down,</hi> e're the <hi>other</hi> can be thought throughly <hi>esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished?</hi> as if the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> could be well built upon nothing but its <hi>own ruines:</hi> or like the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol,</hi> it could not be <hi>firmly founded,</hi> but where the <hi>builders</hi> find a <hi>dead Mans skul.</hi> So that if you take a strickt Survey of any of these, you will find the Walls <hi>graced</hi> (as they call it) with <hi>several Hic jacet's;</hi> of which kind of <hi>Monuments,</hi> the more there are, the more <hi>beautiful</hi> and <hi>gorgeous</hi> is the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> esteemed. Thus do they make <hi>Honour</hi> a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal,</hi> or <hi>Horsleach,</hi> hungry for want of <hi>Mans flesh,</hi> and thirsting after <hi>blood;</hi> and intimate to the World that there is a <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> so incensed, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:212056:13"/>nothing will apease him but <hi>Human Sacrifice,</hi> and that his <hi>Votaries</hi> must <hi>offer</hi> nothing at his <hi>Altar,</hi> but like the <hi>Priests</hi> of <hi>Baal,</hi> with the <hi>dreadful Cerimony</hi> of <hi>Cutting</hi> and <hi>Wounding.</hi> This kind of <hi>Religion</hi> I dare not <hi>contradict</hi> or <hi>reprove,</hi> it being the <hi>constant resolve</hi> of the <hi>Maturest deliberations,</hi> to attempt <hi>Achieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of this <hi>Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>stoutest Champions,</hi> to be blest in these their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, with a <hi>Prosperous success,</hi> of whom he is the most <hi>Honourable</hi> that has the most <hi>Gules</hi> in his <hi>Escutcheon,</hi> and the most happy that has <hi>enroll'd</hi> the greatest number of <hi>Martyrs</hi> in the <hi>Kalender</hi> of <hi>Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, for ought I know, may not be an <hi>errour</hi> in <hi>Planets</hi> of the <hi>Superiour Orbs:</hi> but sure I am, it begets one in the <hi>inferiour</hi> and <hi>sublunary bodies,</hi> who while they look upon these as <hi>true lights,</hi> and <hi>safe guides,</hi> find themselves (as by an <hi>Ignis fatuus) benight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and <hi>seduced.</hi> Noblemen cannot but discern how Gentlemen of <hi>less quality throng</hi> and <hi>croud</hi> to come as <hi>neer</hi> them as is possible, imitating them according to (nay beyond) their <hi>Abilities,</hi> in their <hi>Habit, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> and all pieces of <hi>Gallantry:</hi> Nay, even in their <hi>Vices;</hi> esteeming all things <hi>Lawful,</hi> or at least <hi>Creditable</hi> which are worthy of their pursuit. And
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:212056:13"/>were it not an easie matter for them to bring this foolish and rash way of <hi>Duelling</hi> into contempt, by being neither <hi>examples</hi> nor <hi>countenancers</hi> of it?</p>
            <p>It would be <hi>Arogance</hi> in me, to propose any way for the effecting of this, but my confidence of the Facility of it is (I believe) well grounded, for all Men know, that whosoever kills a Man in a <hi>Duel,</hi> is <hi>Ipso Facto,</hi> to be put to death by the <hi>Law,</hi> and yet the <hi>Fountain</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> and the <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> are one and the same <hi>Person: (Viz.)</hi> The <hi>King:</hi> whom we must Accriminate with absurd and incongruous <hi>contradictions</hi> in his <hi>actions,</hi> if we suppose him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Honour</hi> upon a <hi>Person,</hi> and then immediately make such Laws, which if he obeys 'tis possible for him to preserve. Were there no other means to be used for the <hi>preservation</hi> of a Man's <hi>Honour,</hi> but to <hi>Duel</hi> the person that <hi>assaulted</hi> it, is it to be imagined that there would ever have been so severe a <hi>Law</hi> against <hi>Duelling?</hi> so then, the necessity of <hi>Fighting</hi> must be <hi>removed,</hi> or the <hi>incongruity allowed,</hi> which would be flat <hi>Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Man is <hi>dub'd Knight Banneret</hi> in the <hi>Field,</hi> for some <hi>signal</hi> piece of <hi>Service;</hi> is this <hi>person</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obliged to <hi>challenge</hi> every <hi>Hot-headed Boy,</hi> that shall call him <hi>Coward</hi> at home? or may he not by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:212056:14"/>a <hi>Sober</hi> and <hi>Prudent carriage</hi> maintain his <hi>Honour</hi> without it: and order it so, that the <hi>Pert Youth</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear a <hi>Ridiculous Child,</hi> while he proves himself as <hi>Prudent</hi> as <hi>Stout.</hi> And have we not many <hi>gallant examples</hi> of this temper in the Kingdom? Are there not Men of unquestioned <hi>Valour,</hi> who have made the <hi>Enemy</hi> confess them to be <hi>Lyons,</hi> and yet will suffer these wanton <hi>Kids</hi> to leap into their very <hi>mouths</hi> without harm? By which means (I think) they rather confirm themselves to be <hi>true bred,</hi> than give any man occasion to suppose them <hi>degenerate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (I fancy) I have but one sort of Men left to deal with: <hi>(viz.)</hi> Those that allow <hi>Duels</hi> to he <hi>unlawful,</hi> and consequently <hi>dishonourable;</hi> and yet out of a <hi>vain glorious humour</hi> will venture at all, resolving to purchase the Name of <hi>Man,</hi> though with the <hi>Epethets</hi> of <hi>foolish</hi> or <hi>miserable.</hi> Yet I am of an opinion, that if the good Laws provided in this case were duly executed, much of this <hi>fool-hardiness</hi> would be abated. But I can never hope to convince one by <hi>Reason,</hi> whom the <hi>remissness</hi> of <hi>Justice,</hi> or <hi>abundance</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> has thus emboldned: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will try (if he be not above <hi>Fear</hi>) to deter him, by setting before him the <hi>unequal terms</hi> upon which he must sometimes <hi>fight.</hi> This <hi>Catholique Dueller</hi> must
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:212056:14"/>be supposed to maintain his <hi>Honour</hi> in all places, and with all persons: If so, than fancying him to be small in <hi>stature,</hi> or to have any <hi>natural defect,</hi> or <hi>impediment</hi> whereby he is rendred uncapable of bearing up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst one every way compleat, is it probable that such a one should be <hi>Victorious?</hi> So that this poor <hi>Lamb</hi> goes into the field but as a <hi>victim</hi> to <hi>Honour,</hi> and dies with double disadvantage to be first <hi>abused,</hi> and afterwards <hi>killed</hi> for it: and all the benefit that he reaps by it, is the <hi>Encomium</hi> of <hi>pretty mettl'd fellow,</hi> and the <hi>Elegy, of a thou sand pitties.</hi> Thus does he gain <hi>compassion</hi> instead of <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Fools Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice</hi> instead of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though Probability gives this <hi>Gyant</hi> the <hi>Victory,</hi> yet 'tis possible that <hi>Fortune</hi> may so guide the <hi>Pigmy's</hi> sword, that it may reach the heart of this <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> who upon such an accident, falls with all <hi>imaginable disgrace;</hi> so that in an <hi>unequal Duel</hi> 'tis almost impossible for either of the <hi>Sword-men</hi> to obtain even that which the <hi>vauntingest huff</hi> miscalls <hi>Honour;</hi> for in the <hi>first instance</hi> the <hi>infirmities</hi> of the <hi>Enemy</hi> are traduced as <hi>blots</hi> in the <hi>Escucheon</hi> of the <hi>Victor,</hi> and in the last, the Conquest is wholly <hi>ascribed</hi> to <hi>Chance:</hi> and therefore I approve of the answer given by a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a great Impediment in his Eyes, desired
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:212056:15"/>his <hi>Antagonist</hi> (who Challenged him at <hi>Rapier</hi>) to meet him in a <hi>dark Cellar</hi> with a <hi>Hatchet:</hi> But fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying all desired <hi>Parity,</hi> persons equal in <hi>Strength, Skill,</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> how Casual then is the Event! Certainly in such a case the <hi>Victor</hi> must allow him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self indebted to <hi>Fortune</hi> for his <hi>Success,</hi> because (as I said) there is an equallity. Might not such <hi>Despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoes</hi> as these, be perswaded upon a <hi>mutual affront,</hi> to <hi>draw cuts</hi> for their lives, agreeing that he who drew the shortest should <hi>hang himself</hi> to give the other <hi>satisfaction?</hi> Why not? For the <hi>prudence</hi> of this way 'tis certainly the best, because the <hi>equallest,</hi> having its whole dependance upon a <hi>casualty;</hi> whereas in a <hi>Duel</hi> one of the <hi>Combatants</hi> may have the advantage of <hi>skill.</hi> For the <hi>mettle</hi> of it, 'tis the stoutest, because one of them must assuredly <hi>dye;</hi> whereas in a <hi>Duel</hi> a <hi>Coward</hi> may encourage himself with the hopes of being <hi>disarmed,</hi> or <hi>lightly wounded:</hi> For the <hi>mercy</hi> of it, 'tis the most commendable; for here only one perisheth, whereas in a <hi>Duel</hi> both may be <hi>slain,</hi> or <hi>desperately hurt:</hi> For the <hi>satisfaction</hi> of it, 'tis the <hi>compleatest;</hi> for here a Man has <hi>Plenary Restitution,</hi> made by the <hi>Offenders</hi> own <hi>hands,</hi> while he lives at peace and liberty, to enjoy the <hi>happiness:</hi> whereas in a <hi>Duel,</hi> though he does kill his Adversary, yet the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:212056:15"/>
               <hi>Laws</hi> call a Man into question, and perhaps take away his Life: For the <hi>pleasure</hi> of it, 'tis (without doubt) the most <hi>ticking;</hi> for here you may please your self with seeing your <hi>Enemy</hi> do <hi>Execution</hi> artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially upon himself, whilst you stand by as a <hi>safe Spectator:</hi> whereas in a <hi>Duel</hi> the <hi>danger</hi> much abates of the <hi>Lechery:</hi> And lastly, for the <hi>Honour</hi> of it, 'tis far the <hi>greatest:</hi> for here the <hi>vanquisht</hi> is but <hi>hang'd:</hi> and that only in sight of two or three <hi>Friends</hi> (perhaps:) whereas in a <hi>Duel,</hi> the <hi>conquerour</hi> many times suffers a more <hi>ignominious death,</hi> even among <hi>Malefactors,</hi> and before thousands of <hi>beholders.</hi> What a <hi>Ridiculous Soloecism</hi> in Morrals is <hi>Duelling!</hi> when even so <hi>Bruitish</hi> a <hi>proposition</hi> as this, should appear far more <hi>Rational</hi> and <hi>Eligible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there is one thing yet behind, which hugely agravates the indiscretion of it, that indeed whereby the name of <hi>Folly</hi> is swallowed up in madness: That is the use of <hi>Seconds.</hi> How this custome crept into the World, I cannot tell, but to me it seems the most <hi>absurd</hi> that can be thought of: I am not so well versed in Martial History, as to give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Original</hi> of these. But sure I am, if they were intended for good, their Design is strangely perverted: Were they <hi>Spectatours</hi> only to see that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:212056:16"/>no <hi>Foul play</hi> (as they call it) be offered: or such as might be <hi>assistant,</hi> as <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> it were tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But as they are now used, 'tis a <hi>Frenzy</hi> not to be <hi>Parallel'd.</hi> I need not inform the compleat <hi>Dueller</hi> that the <hi>Mode</hi> now adays, is for all the <hi>Seconds</hi> to draw at once with the <hi>Principal;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them the <hi>Engagement</hi> is as <hi>vigorous</hi> as if each were the very person that first gave the affront. This indeed is <hi>Honour</hi> in it's <hi>purity!</hi> wherein the most <hi>curious eye</hi> cannot <hi>discern</hi> the least <hi>dregs:</hi> this is that <hi>excellently refined Mettal,</hi> which will endure the nicest touch of the choicest <hi>Loadstone!</hi> The <hi>Principal</hi> may be encouraged by <hi>Passion,</hi> or animated by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,</hi> but here's he that will <hi>fight</hi> with any man in the quarrel of a <hi>Friend;</hi> nay, of a <hi>Stranger,</hi> quickned by no other <hi>Spur</hi> than that of <hi>Honour:</hi> In Heavens Name! what irreconcileable <hi>absurdities?</hi> what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable <hi>dangers</hi> do men voluntarily run into? was ever, (no 'tis impossible) any thing in the world so <hi>heteradox</hi> to <hi>reason,</hi> nay, to <hi>common-sence,</hi> as this? for a man to go into the <hi>Field,</hi> to meet he knows not whom, perhaps a <hi>bosom Friend:</hi> to fight in justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of he knows not what, it may be giving the <hi>Lye:</hi> to lose his life in <hi>Complezance,</hi> he knows not how: possibly by being over-power'd by two or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:212056:16"/>three This is an <hi>Intreague,</hi> that for my Som I cannot comprehend: A <hi>Gordian knot</hi> so interwoven, and complicated, that were <hi>Alexander</hi> himself alive, it would <hi>nonplus</hi> both him and his Sword. What can be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th Riddle of this! Do men propose safety to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, by electing <hi>Seconds?</hi> If they do, I deny their <hi>Major.</hi> For if either of the Seconds fall, I suppose (pardon me if I err) he that flew him, may if he please, return to the assistance of his <hi>own principal;</hi> and then there are two against one. So that one chosen for a safe guard, may become either through his want of skill, or good luck, destructive to the Person for whom he Engages. But there is yet a a greater inconvenience that attends this <hi>Folly:</hi> For when only two fight, 'tis very possible that satisfaction may be had without the Death of either. But in this case where four or six engage, 'tis not to be imagined they shall all escape, and all Men know that the Death of either, renders all parties concerned as obnoxious to the <hi>Law,</hi> as if each were the man that had given him his mortal wound. In my apprehension, such undertakers seem to have no other <hi>Plot,</hi> than by setting themselves beyond the bounds of safety, to let the World know how little
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:212056:17"/>they fear <hi>Death:</hi> And does not every <hi>fellow</hi> that is possest with <hi>Despair,</hi> a <hi>Frenzy,</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> or what you will call it, while he <hi>Stabs, Hangs,</hi> or <hi>Drowns</hi> himself, deserve to be enrolled among these <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> of Honour, upon the same account? I think he does.</p>
            <p>But to what purpose do I argue, when even mens <hi>own inclinations</hi> supersede my <hi>reasonings.</hi> In this case men by a <hi>Diabolical</hi> kind of <hi>infatuation, do</hi> that which they <hi>would not,</hi> and confute the <hi>succession</hi> of <hi>Action</hi> and <hi>Election.</hi> 'Tis in vain to diswade a man from an enterprize, when he says himself,
<q>
                  <l>—Video meliora probo{que}</l>
                  <l>Deteriora sequor.—</l>
               </q> Nor can I rationally expect such mens compliance with <hi>my arguments,</hi> who cannot be obedient to their <hi>own wills.</hi> I dare appeal to any Man, whether he ever went into the <hi>Field</hi> (to fight a <hi>Duel</hi> I mean) <hi>unconcernedly:</hi> or having slain his <hi>adversary,</hi> returned joyfully. And can this be <hi>true Honour</hi> that has <hi>Regret</hi> for its <hi>Companion,</hi> and <hi>Sorrow</hi> for its <hi>Lackey?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having gone so far, as to decry <hi>Duel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and to declare it as my opinion, that a <hi>wounded reputation</hi> is not to be cured by <hi>weapon-salve:</hi> It may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:212056:17"/>be expected that I should propose some more <hi>justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable</hi> way for the satisfaction of a <hi>Person injured</hi> in his <hi>good Name,</hi> by the reproaches of another.</p>
            <p>But I conceive it improper to prepare <hi>Restora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> before a Patient is satisfied that he is distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered: and Rude, thus to endeavour to <hi>drench</hi> him into Health against his Will; and take away the edge of that, which he calls a <hi>good stomach,</hi> when, indeed, it is <hi>appetitus caninus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the attempt I have made, chance to work any way upon the Spirits of the <hi>Duellist,</hi> so as to bring him to himself, out of those <hi>raving fits,</hi> in which there is no coming <hi>neer him,</hi> without <hi>danger;</hi> I have those <hi>Lenitives</hi> in store, that will not (I hope) prove so <hi>Ganenically nauseating,</hi> but that he may down with them: nor so <hi>Spirituous,</hi> and <hi>Chimical,</hi> but that he may take them safely: such as I dare say, will be conducing to <hi>long Life,</hi> and effect the <hi>Cure</hi> (as the <hi>Quack</hi>'s Bill runs) without <hi>hindrance</hi> of <hi>busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> or <hi>loss</hi> of <hi>reputation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this first <hi>Essay</hi> find the least of a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reception among Men, I shall adventure upon a second endeavour, to shew how in most cases a Man's <hi>Honour</hi> may be <hi>preserv'd</hi> without <hi>Duels:</hi> and remove the <hi>Tyranical imposition</hi> of sitting at a Feast
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:212056:18"/>with a <hi>Sword</hi> hanging over our heads, fastned only by a hair. Yet least I should never meet with this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement; I only say in general, he that will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve his <hi>Honour</hi> entire, and his <hi>Reputation</hi> sound; let him be morally good; let him behave himself sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missively towards his Superiours, Valliantly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Enemies, Civilly towards his Equals, and Courteously towards his Inferiours; such a Deportment as this will prove a <hi>gag</hi> to <hi>Malice,</hi> and a <hi>scourge</hi> to <hi>Slander:</hi> and whosoever is of this temper, will soon find that the satisfaction a man gives to the World, by his own life, is better than that which he reaps to himself by another Man's Death.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>